Finding Aid for Paul C. Heaton papers, 1997-2001
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Paul C. Heaton papers 1997-2001
Heaton, Paul C.
1 linear ft.
0679 Aa 2
Paul C. Heaton was the co-chair of the Ypsilanti Campaign for Equality and the Traverse City Campaign Against Discrimination, organizations fighting for gay rights in reference to human rights ordinances in their respective cities. The collection includes correspondence, political documents, and flyers and published articles documenting the efforts of these two organizations, but also includes general information about the campaigns in Ypsilanti and Traverse City.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Paul C. Heaton (donor no. 9742 ) in June 2006.
The collection is open to research.
Paul C. Heaton was actively involved in political campaigns dealing with human rights ordinances in the cities of Ypsilanti and Traverse City, Michigan. He served as co-chair of the Ypsilanti Campaign for Equality and the Traverse City Campaign Against Discrimination, organizations that sought to fight anti-gay initiatives in relation to these ordinances.
The human rights ordinance controversy surfaced in Ypsilanti in February 1997 when a local print shop refused to print raffle tickets for Tri-Pride, a lesbian, gay, bisexual and transgender Eastern Michigan student group because of the type of group that they represented. As a result, concerned Ypsilanti citizens proposed a nondiscrimination ordinance to the city that would prevent discrimination based on an individual's sexual orientation, among other aspects, like race and religion. The Ypsilanti City Council passed this ordinance on December 16, 1997.
In March 1998, an anti-ordinance group known as the Citizens Opposing Special Treatment (COST) proposed a ballot initiative that would repeal the nondiscrimination ordinance. On May 5, 1998, a special election was called, with Ypsilanti citizens ultimately voting to uphold the ordinance.
In Traverse City, anti-gay groups sought a ballot proposal that would "prohibit the city from enacting, adopting, enforcing or administering any ordinance, regulation, rule or policy which grants special minority or protected status, quota preference or other preferential treatment based upon homosexual, lesbian, or bisexual orientation, conduct, or relationship." The ballot proposal failed after a November 6, 2001 vote.
The collection has been organized by human rights ordinance campaign, Ypsilanti and Traverse City. The Ypsilanti Campaign series (0.4 linear ft., 1997-1998) and the Traverse City Campaign series (0.4 linear ft., 2000-2001) include correspondence, political documents, flyers and published articles, and materials detailing fundraising efforts and election strategy. The collection primarily documents the efforts of the Ypsilanti Campaign for Equality and the Traverse City Campaign Against Discrimination, but includes general information about the campaigns as well.
The collection also documents Paul C. Heaton's involvement in a Michigan Equality training program. Materials include handouts and training materials detailing how to organize a successful human rights ordinances political campaign.
Subjects:
Heaton, Paul C.; Ypsilanti Campaign for Equality.; Traverse City Campaign Against Discrimination.; Michigan Equality (Organization); Gay rights--Michigan--Ypsilanti.; Gay rights--Michigan--Traverse City.; Ypsilanti (Mich.)--Politics and government.; Traverse City (Mich.)--Politics and government.
- Ypsilanti campaign
  - Campaign correspondence
    - Incoming (Box 1)
    - Outgoing (Box 1)
  - Charter amendment (repeal) (Box 1)
  - Citizens for Community, 1997 (Box 1)
  - Citizens Opposing Special Treatment
    (COST)
    - General (Box 1)
    - Rally (Box 1)
  - Clippings and published articles (Box 1)
  - Election day (Box 1)
  - Endorsements (Box 1)
  - Flyers and mailings
    - General (Box 1)
    - Religious flyer (Box 1)
  - Fundraising
    - Autographed raffle tickets (Box 1)
    - Financial support letter (Box 1)
  - Ordinance (Box 1)
  - Petitions (Box 1)
    (controversy)
  - Press releases (Box 1)
  - Speeches and special events
    - Award speech (Box 1)
    - City Council presentation, February 1998 (Box 1)
    - Human Rights Campaign equality awards, October 1998 (Box 1)
    - Lambda Legal Defense and Education Fund, March 1999 (Box 1)
    - Outloud chorus concert, November 1998 (Box 1)
    - Press conference, April 1998 (Box 1)
    - "What worked for us": highlights from the Ypsilanti Campaign for Equality, November 1998 (Box 1)
  - Strategy (Box 1)
  - Ypsilanti Campaign for Equality
    - Agendas and notes (Box 1)
    - Campaign meetings and organization (Box 1)
- Traverse City campaign
  - August 8, 2000 primary (Box 1)
  - Ballot (Box 1)
  - Clippings and letters
    - General, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Forums, articles, editorials (Box 1)
    - Letters to editor (Box 1)
    - Northern Express, elsewhere outside of Traverse City (Box 1)
  - Endorsements
    - General (Box 1)
    - Doctors (Box 1)
    - People of faith (Box 1)
  - Opponents
    - General (Box 1)
    - Phelps, Rev. Fred, January 2001 (Box 1)
    - Agendas and minutes (Box 1)
    - Campaign plan (Box 1)
    - Public relations (Box 1)
- Michigan Equality
  - Campaign training
    - 2001 (Box 1)
    - 2002
      - General (Box 1)
      - Drafts (Box 1)